MEGHENDRA SINGH

MS-Computer Science & Applications

meghs@vt.edu ◆ +1 (540) 449 8769

SUMMARY:

- Pursuing Master's degree at Virginia Tech, graduating in May 2018.
- Machine Learning and programming enthusiast with 4 years of experience, seeking full time job opportunities.

TECHNICAL SKILLS: Java, Python, C, C++, PHP, R, HTML5, CSS, JavaScript, REST, JSON, APIs, Shell, Oracle, MySQL, Android SDK, Git, Scikit-learn, Linux, Statistics – Classification and Regression, Lucene, Selenium, Keras.

TOOLS: Eclipse, NetBeans, Jupyter Notebook, PyCharm, pgAdmin, MATLAB, Apache-Tomcat

EDUCATION:

Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, VA, United States

Aug 2018 - Present

Master of Science (Computer Science & Applications)

GPA - 3.85/4.0

Courses: Data Analytics, Theory of Algorithms, Software Engineering, Models of HCI

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE:

IT Analyst, TCS Innovation Labs, Pune, India

May 2012 – Jun 2016

Worked as a Data Analyst and JAVA developer.

Human Data Collection Platform (HDCP):

Feb 2016 - Jun 2016

- > Technologies Used: J2EE, REST, Linux, JSON, Android SDK, PostgreSQL, Geocoder and Google Maps APIs.
- > Developed android apps and web services for collecting, visualizing and curating real time sensor data from user's smart devices.

Social Sim Engine (SSE)

Sept 2015 – Jan 2016

- Technologies Used: Java, Eclipse RCP, Hibernate, Spring, MySQL, Weka
- > Developed workflows and dashboards for the SSE desktop application. Developed plugins for search, retrieval and parsing of regression models in SSE.

Human Centric Systems, TCS Innovation Labs, India

May 2012 – Aug 2015

- > Technologies Used: Java, Python, Pandas, scikit-learn, REST, JSON, Repast, Backbone.JS, NetLogo, GAMA
- Implemented various research projects like, Multi-Source Data Miner, EnterpriseSim and BehavCaster.

Team Lead, Tata Consultancy Services, Trivandrum, India

Jan 2012 – May 2012

Conducted initial Research & Proof of Concept for projects along with software and architecture development.

Lead a team of five, in a project involving design, development, testing and maintenance for an insurance services organization.

ACADEMIC PROJECTS:

- Forest Detector: Developed a web service for classifying forest cover in aerial images of continental US using deep learning (Convolutional Neural Networks), using Python, Pandas, Flask, TensorFlow, Keras.
- ➤ EpiViz.: Designed and implemented an interactive framework for visualizing and tracking epidemic data, using Python, Pandas, Plotly, Oracle DB, Linux
- ➤ Shot Predictor: Developed an application for predicting vaccine adoption using classification algorithms like:

 Decision trees, ANNs, Bagging and AdaBoost, using R, Shiny.
- ➤ ApartMates: Web application to enable delegation and sharing of responsibilities and expenses in shared apartments, built using: JavaEE, JSF, PrimeFaces, JPA, MySQL, HTML5, JavaScript, JAX-RS.

ACHIEVEMENTS:

- > Ranked in the top 10% in KDD Cup 2013, Microsoft Academic Search Author Disambiguation Challenge.
- Microsoft certified specialist: Programming in HTML5 with JavaScript and CSS3.
- > Received TCS Star of the learner's group and Service and commitment awards for my contributions during various projects.
- > Statements of accomplishment with distinction from Coursera.com in: Machine Learning, Core Concepts in Data Analysis and Startup Engineering.